<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
<title>Water Features</title>
<para>
This table gives estimates of various soil water features. The estimates are used in land use planning that involves engineering considerations.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="italic">Hydrologic soil groups</emphasis>
are based on estimates of runoff potential. Soils are assigned to one of four groups according to the rate of water infiltration when the soils are not protected by vegetation, are thoroughly wet, and receive precipitation from long-duration storms.
</para>
<para>The four hydrologic soil groups are:</para>
<para>
Group A. Soils having a high infiltration rate (low runoff potential) when thoroughly wet. These consist mainly of deep, well drained to excessively drained sands or gravelly sands. These soils have a high rate of water transmission.
</para>
<para>
Group B. Soils having a moderate infiltration rate when thoroughly wet. These consist chiefly of moderately deep or deep, moderately well drained or well drained soils that have moderately fine texture to moderately coarse texture. These soils have a moderate rate of water transmission.
</para>
<para>
Group C. Soils having a slow infiltration rate when thoroughly wet. These consist chiefly of soils having a layer that impedes the downward movement of water or soils of moderately fine texture or fine texture. These soils have a slow rate of water transmission.
</para>
<para>
Group D. Soils having a very slow infiltration rate (high runoff potential) when thoroughly wet. These consist chiefly of clays that have a high shrink-swell potential, soils that have a high water table, soils that have a claypan or clay layer at or near the surface, and soils that are shallow over nearly impervious material. These soils have a very slow rate of water transmission.
</para>
<para>
If a soil is assigned to a dual hydrologic group (A/D, B/D, or C/D), the first letter is for drained areas and the second is for undrained areas.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="italic">Surface runoff</emphasis>
refers to the loss of water from an area by flow over the land surface. Surface runoff classes are based on slope, climate, and vegetative cover. The concept indicates relative runoff for very specific conditions. It is assumed that the surface of the soil is bare and that the retention of surface water resulting from irregularities in the ground surface is minimal. The classes are negligible, very low, low, medium, high, and very high.
</para>
<para>
The
<emphasis role="italic">months</emphasis>
in the table indicate the portion of the year in which a water table, ponding, and/or flooding is most likely to be a concern.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="italic">Water table</emphasis>
refers to a saturated zone in the soil. The water features table indicates, by month, depth to the top (
<emphasis role="italic">upper limit</emphasis>
) and base (
<emphasis role="italic">lower limit</emphasis>
) of the saturated zone in most years. Estimates of the upper and lower limits are based mainly on observations of the water table at selected sites and on evidence of a saturated zone, namely grayish colors or mottles (redoximorphic features) in the soil. A saturated zone that lasts for less than a month is not considered a water table.
(
<emphasis role="italic">Kind</emphasis>
) The kind of water table if a seasonal high water table exists in the soil. Entries are either apparent or perched. A perched water table is where free water is restricted from moving downward in the soil by a restrictive feature, in most cases a hard pan. Therefore, there is a dry layer of soil underneath a wet layer. An apparent water table is one where there is free water present in all horizons from its upper boundary to below 2 meters or to the depth of observation. The water table kind listed is for the first major component in the map unit.


</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="italic">Ponding</emphasis>
is standing water in a closed depression. Unless a drainage system is installed, the water is removed only by percolation, transpiration, or evaporation. The table indicates
<emphasis role="italic">surface water depth</emphasis>
and the
<emphasis role="italic">duration</emphasis>
and
<emphasis role="italic">frequency</emphasis>
of ponding. Duration is expressed as
<emphasis role="italic">very brief</emphasis>
if less than 2 days,
<emphasis role="italic">brief</emphasis>
if 2 to 7 days,
<emphasis role="italic">long</emphasis>
if 7 to 30 days, and
<emphasis role="italic">very long</emphasis>
if more than 30 days. Frequency is expressed as none, rare, occasional, and frequent.
<emphasis role="italic">None</emphasis>
means that ponding is not probable;
<emphasis role="italic">rare</emphasis>
that it is unlikely but possible under unusual weather conditions (the chance of ponding is nearly 0 percent to 5 percent in any year);
<emphasis role="italic">occasional</emphasis>
that it occurs, on the average, once or less in 2 years (the chance of ponding is 5 to 50 percent in any year); and
<emphasis role="italic">frequent</emphasis>
that it occurs, on the average, more than once in 2 years (the chance of ponding is more than 50 percent in any year).
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="italic">Flooding</emphasis>
is the temporary inundation of an area caused by overflowing streams, by runoff from adjacent slopes, or by tides. Water standing for short periods after rainfall or snowmelt is not considered flooding, and water standing in swamps and marshes is considered ponding rather than flooding.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="italic">Duration</emphasis>
and
<emphasis role="italic">frequency</emphasis>
are estimated. Duration is expressed as
<emphasis role="italic">extremely brief</emphasis>
if 0.1 hour to 4 hours,
<emphasis role="italic">very brief</emphasis>
if 4 hours to 2 days,
<emphasis role="italic">brief</emphasis>
if 2 to 7 days,
<emphasis role="italic">long</emphasis>
if 7 to 30 days, and
<emphasis role="italic">very long</emphasis>
if more than 30 days. Frequency is expressed as none, very rare, rare, occasional, frequent, and very frequent.
<emphasis role="italic">None</emphasis>
means that flooding is not probable;
<emphasis role="italic">very rare</emphasis>
that it is very unlikely but possible under extremely unusual weather conditions (the chance of flooding is less than 1 percent in any year);
<emphasis role="italic">rare</emphasis>
that it is unlikely but possible under unusual weather conditions (the chance of flooding is 1 to 5 percent in any year);
<emphasis role="italic">occasional</emphasis>
that it occurs infrequently under normal weather conditions (the chance of flooding is 5 to 50 percent in any year);
<emphasis role="italic">frequent</emphasis>
that it is likely to occur often under normal weather conditions (the chance of flooding is more than 50 percent in any year but is less than 50 percent in all months in any year); and
<emphasis role="italic">very frequent</emphasis>
that it is likely to occur very often under normal weather conditions (the chance of flooding is more than 50 percent in all months of any year).
</para>
<para>
The information is based on evidence in the soil profile, namely thin strata of gravel, sand, silt, or clay deposited by floodwater; irregular decrease in organic matter content with increasing depth; and little or no horizon development.
</para>
<para>
Also considered are local information about the extent and levels of flooding and the relation of each soil on the landscape to historic floods. Information on the extent of flooding based on soil data is less specific than that provided by detailed engineering surveys that delineate flood-prone areas at specific flood frequency levels.
</para>
</section>